<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Cubox | Daniel Cadenas]]></title>
  <link href="http://dcadenas.github.com/blog/categories/cubox/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dcadenas.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-03-22T02:38:04-03:00</updated>
  <id>http://dcadenas.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Daniel Cadenas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Ruby gems]]></title>
    <link href="http://dcadenas.github.com/blog/2010/04/02/new-ruby-gems/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-02T16:45:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://dcadenas.github.com/blog/2010/04/02/new-ruby-gems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Oops! It's been a while since the last time I updated my blog.
I promise I'll try to get back to business and write more often whenever I find some time.</p>

<p>First of all, many months ago I joined <a href="http://cuboxlabs.com">Cubox</a>, a new uruguayan startup that works for many US clients including partnership and offshore work with renowned Rails shops. We are continuously growing and we are always happy to add talented developers to our team so if you are interested and are passionate about Ruby, Rails and agile development just email us.</p>

<p>We believe in open source, we use it in all our projects and we also contribute to the community. Here is an update of my latest new gems which were not covered in this blog. I hope you find them useful, click on the links for more info:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://github.com/dcadenas/preforker">Preforker</a>: Easily create preforking servers (like Unicorn architecture)</li>
<li><a href="http://github.com/cubox/rankable_graph">Rankable Graph</a>: Calculates the pagerank of medium sized graphs (some millions of nodes).</li>
<li><a href="http://github.com/dcadenas/state_pattern">State Pattern</a>: A classical implementation of the state pattern.</li>
<li><a href="http://github.com/dcadenas/stubborn">Stubborn</a>: Helps finding missing external API stubs in your tests.</li>
<li><a href="http://github.com/dcadenas/google_set">Google Set</a>: API for Google Sets.</li>
<li><a href="http://github.com/dcadenas/change_watcher">Change Watcher</a>: Helps keeping a log of changes. Useful to store scraped info from cron scripts.</li>
</ul>


<p>So check them out and contribute!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
